嘿, 你们好
hey, what's up guys
我是Cherno, 欢迎来到我的OpenGL系列教程
my name is Cherno, and welcome back to my OpenGL series
那么, 今天我们要讲的是顶点数组
so, today we're going to be talking all about vertex array
以及我们实际上如何抽象它们
and how we can actually abstract them
如果你还不知道顶点数组是什么
if you don't know what a vertex array is
就去看看我制作的那期视频
check out the video that I made
解释了, 什么是顶点数组, 如何使用它们, 以及我们为什么需要使用它们
explain what vertex arrays are, and how to use them, and why we need to use them
就像我在那期视频中提到的, 我想它们是可选的
as I mentioned in that video, they are kind of optional to use I guess
但现在的趋势似乎是使用它们
but the trend seems to be moving towards using them
所以, 抛开语义, 抛开细节
so, sematics aside, details aside
让我们来看看这个
let's actually get into this
并想办法在OpenGL中抽象一个顶点数组
and figure out how we can abstract a vertex array in OpenGL
那么, 首先, 我们为什么要使用顶点数组
so, first of all, what is it, why exactly should we be using a vertex array
这个抽象的目的是什么
and what is this, what is the goal of this abstraction, right
为什么我们需要抽象
why do we want to abstract
这是另一件你可以思考的事情, 当你抽象一些东西的时候
this is another thing that you can actually think about, when you're abstracting something
这并不是必须的, 你知道的, 让我们把它移到我自己的类中
it's not necessarily like, you know, let's just move this out into my own classes
但是你们为什么要把它转移到你们自己的类中, 对吧
but why are you moving it into your own classes, right
为什么我必须为这种概念创建类, 对吧
why do I have to create class specifically for this kind of concept, right
为什么我不直接用OpenGL的代码
why can't I just use OpenGL code
很多时候, 这似乎只是因为我希望它在我自己的名称空间中
a lot of the times, it seems to be just because I want it in my own namespace
我想说这是我自己的东西, 对吧
and I want to call it my own thing, right
这并不是抽象事物的真正原因
that's not really a reason for abstracting something
我是说在很多情况下都是这样
I mean it can be in a lot of cases
因为你显然想要简化你的接口, 并保持一致
because you obviously want to kind of streamline your api, and keep it consistent
所以有时候, 你只需要创建一个非常非常小的包裹, 它什么都不做
so sometimes, you just end up creating a very very thin wrapper, that does nothing else
但主要是改变函数的名称
but basically change the name of a function
而那也是可以的
and that's also kind of okay
但是当你考虑顶点数组的时候
but when you're thinking about vertex array
当你考虑所有这些OpenGL概念时, 想想看
and when you think about all these OpenGL concepts, have a think about
为什么我要把它抽象出来
why am I abstracting this
为什么我要把这个移到类中去
why am I moving this out into a class
这样做的目的是什么
what is the purpose of this
我希望通过这样做实现什么目标
what do I hope to achieve with this
具体的目标是, 这样你就可以告诉自己
and specifically the goal of that is, so that you can tell yourself
这是列表, 这是我在我的需求中做的功能列表
this is the list, this is the list of features I made these in my requirements
现在, 让我们建立一些东西, 它们实际上可以促进这一点
now, let's build something that, they can actually facilitate that
对于我们来说, 顶点数组需要做的
for us, what a vertex array needs to be able to do
就是希望将顶点缓冲区与某种布局联系在一起, 对吧
is hopefully tie together a vertex buffer with some kind of layout, right
所以顶点缓冲区就是有数据的缓冲区, 它们没有实际的概念
so vertex buffers are just buffers with data, they have no actual concept of
比如你知道的
like you know
前三个浮点数是位置, 它们是浮点型
the first three floats are a position and they're floats
它们有这么大之类的
and they're this big and all of that
没有类型或大小之类的概念
there's no concept of types or size or anything like that
它只是实际数据的普通缓冲区
it's just a plain buffer of actual data
我们会有一堆字节
we would just have a bunch of bytes
所以比如像每个字节是什么
so how like what is each byte
比如这些顶点有多大等等
like how big is these vertex all of that kind of stuff
那些是顶点数组真正代表的
that is what a vertex array is really for
它应该把缓冲区和实际布局联系在一起
it's supposed to tie together that buffer with an actual layout
你可以添加一个索引缓冲区到里面, 做一些其他的事情
and you can add an index buffer into that and do a bunch of other stuff
我们稍后会讨论的
which we can talk about later
但这就是它们最初存在的基本原因
but that's the basic idea of why they exist in the first place
顶点数组对象是OpenGL存储那种状态的方式
and a vertex array object is OpenGL's way of kind of storing that state
那么当我们考虑创建这个接口时, 我们需要做的是
so what we need to do, as we think about creating this api right now
我们需要一些东西来创建一个顶点数组
is we need something that hopefully I can just create a vertex array
然后我可以给它一个特定的布局
and then I can maybe give it a certain layout
然后添加一个缓冲区或者类似的东西
and then add a buffer to it or something like that
或者我只是创建一个顶点数组, 它是一系列缓冲区, 可以是一个或多个
or maybe I just create vertex array, which is a series of buffers can be one or more
然后告诉我创建的顶点数组
and then I just tell the vertex array that I've made
嘿, 我想要这种布局
hey, I want this kind of layout
希望这已经足够了就像我们要做的
and hopefully that'll kind of be enough for like what we're trying to do
然后, 当我绑定顶点数组时
and then later on, when I bind the vertex array
我应该能够调用顶点数组来绑定到我自己的对象上
I should be able to just call like vertex array to bind on my own object
那应该会把所有的东西联系在一起
and that should kind of tie everything together
实际上你知道用OpenGL绑定数组
and actually you know bind the array in terms of OpenGL
所以就那样想想吧
so think about it that way
当我开始提取这个的时候, 希望那更有意义
hopefully that will make more sense, as I start extracting this
但真正对我们重要的是
but the really the thing that is important for us
我们希望能够定义某种布局
is we want to be able to define some kind of layout
这种布局也可能是我们希望在CPU端存在的东西
and this layout may be something that we also want to have exist on the CPU side
这样我们就可以读取实际的顶点缓冲数据
so that we can maybe read our actual vertex buffer data
对于调试, 这是另一个有用的东西
this is another useful thing for debugging
我们并不是100%需要这样做, 因为有工具
it's not like 100% necessary for us to do this, because there are tools
布局实际上是在显卡上调试数据
the layout is actually debug data that's on the GPU
使用我们为显卡指定的布局
using the layout we specified for the GPU and all that
但CPU方面, 有时候看到数据上面的顶点是很有用的
but still CPU sides, sometimes it's useful to actually see our vertex above a data
能够读懂并理解它, 为此我们确实需要一个布局
and actually be able to read it and like interpret it, and for that we do need a layout
所以我们确实需要一种方法来把这些东西存储在CPU上
so we do need a way of actually storing the stuff on the CPU
就像我能想到的一个例子, 不只是为了调试
like one example of that just off the top of my head is, like not just for debugging
但如果我们想要某种缓存的话
but maybe if we wanted to like have like some kind of picking cache
这样我们就可以读出模型中的每个三角形
so that we can actually read each triangle of our model
所以当用户想要点击的时候, 用鼠标按钮点击屏幕上的某个地方
so that when the user like clicks, click somewhere on the screen with their mouse button
我们可以选择那个对象, 为此我们需要触发数组
we can actually select that object, and for that we need to fire array
实际上, 看看它是否与模型中的三角形相交
and actually see if it intersects the triangle that is part of our model
对此我们可能会喜欢
and for that we might want to like
我们可能想要在CPU端存储顶点缓冲区
we might want to actually store the vertex buffer from the CPU side
这样我们就可以对那个三角形做碰撞率测试
so that we can actually you know do that rate kind of collision test against that triangle
这是我们为什么要那么做的一个例子, 但我的观点是
so that's like one example of why we might want to do that, but my point being that
这对我们创建缓冲区布局对象很有用
it's useful for us to actually create some kind of like buffer layout object
实际上, 这是我们今天要做的另一件事
which is another thing that we'll actually do today
总之, 我知道我已经讲了5分钟了
so anyway, I know I've been talking for like 5min now
那么我们把这些都剪掉, 我不会在视频中把它们都剪掉
so let's just cut all that, I'm not gonna cut all it literally in the video
但我们现在要讲一些代码了
but we are gonna jump into some code right now
我们会看到如何抽象这个顶点数组对象
and we're gonna see how we can actually abstract this vertex array object stuff
那么看一下这里的代码
so looking through our code over here
很大的部分, 我猜, 是顶点数组的一部分
the big part that's kind of, I guess, part of our vertex array
真的只有这些吗
is really just kind of this
但它还有这个, 对吧, 这可能看起来不是它的一部分
but it's also this, right, this might not seem like it's part of it
因为我们不需要把这个和一个顶点数组联系起来
because we don't necessarily need to tie this to a vertex array
我们可以只有一个顶点数组, 然后继续重置这个
we could just have a single vertex array, and keep resetting this
关于这个, 我说了很多
I talk a lot about this
我可能会专门制作一期视频来讨论这两者之间的区别
I am probably gonna make a dedicated video talking about the differences between that two
因为我一直在解释, 也许我不该这么做
because I keep explaining myself, I probably shouldn't be
但我们当然可以有一个全局顶点数组对象
but we can of course either have one global vertex array object
并在绑定时不断改变每个缓冲区的布局
and keep changing the layout of each buffer as we bind it
或者我们可以把所有东西都保存在顶点数组对象中
or we can kind of keep everything in vertex array objects
我想顶点数组对象的视频已经讲过了, 只是顶点数组, 可以看看那个
I think the vertex array object video covers that, so just vertex arrays, watch that
但无论如何, 这是把一切联系在一起的东西
but anyway, this is kind of what ties everything together
或者更确切地说, 顶点数组是紧密的, 具有特定的顶点缓冲区和实际布局
or rather vertex arrays are tight, with a certain vertex buffer and an actual layout
那么, 我可能要做的 对吧
so what I what I might want to do, right
如果我随便写一些代码
if I just kind of loosely just dropped up some code
基本上就是我可能想要表示VertexArray va, 对吧
basically is I might want to be able to say VertexArray va, right
它没有必要接收任何参数
it doesn't necessarily need to take anything
然后我们可能要添加一个缓冲区或其他东西, 我不知道, AddBuffer(vb)
then we might want to like add a buffer or something, I don't know, AddBuffer vb
然后我们可能想要添加一个布局或类似的东西, 对吧
and then we might want to add a layout or something like that, right
然后我们可以单独定义布局, 也许我会有一个类叫BufferLayout
and then the layout we might define separately, maybe I'll have a class called BufferLayout
然后我可以定义, 你知道的可能是, 推送第一个东西
and then I can maybe somehow define you know maybe, I push like the first thing
实际上, 我们只有浮点数, 也许我有三个浮点数或其他的
well really we just have like float, so maybe I have like three floats or something
我实际上添加到那个中去, 不知道, 像那个的一些东西吧
that I actually add to that, I don't know, something like that
然后添加这个布局
and then I add the layout
所以这看起来很合理
so this is looking pretty reasonable to me
AddBuffer可能需要一个索引
AddBuffer might take in an index
在某个索引处设置一个缓冲区也很有用
it might be useful to kind of set a buffer at a certain index as well
因为我们可以有多个缓冲区, 它们也可能与布局相关联
because we can have multiple buffers, that might tie in with layouts as well
这里有很多非常复杂的事情你可以做
there's a lot of really complicated things that you can actually do here
就像我说的, 在这个系列中
as I said like, with this series
我们要做的就是, 随着我们的继续
the way that we're kind of going to take it is just, as we go
所以当我需要一个功能时, 我将扩展接口来拥有它
so when I require a feature, I will extend the api to have it
我不会马上写一个完整的接口
I'm not going to try and write a complete api like just like straight away right now
因为那基本上是不可能做到的
because that's basically impossible to do
好了, 所以从这一点来看, 应该有足够的接口让一些东西运转起来
okay, so judging from this, there should be enough to get something working
然后如果我想要绑定它之类的
and then if I want to actually bind it and all of that
我可能只需要va.Bind()
I could probably just do you know va.Bind()
最后对于这个绘制, 绘制代码将保持不变
and finally with this drawer, the drawing code will kind of stay the same
因为这将由我们的渲染器处理
because that'll be handled by our renderer, anyway
但是它是一种绑定顶点数组
but it's kind of bind vertex array
代码应该会是像那样的va.Bind
code kind of should be becoming va.Bind like that
好了, 让我们把这个va.Bind去掉
okay, and let's actually just get rid of this va.Bind
好了, 根据我们刚才做的
okay, so based on what we've just done here
我们来试着创建这个顶点数组
let's try and actually create this vertex array right thing
那么右键点击这里, 去添加新项
so I'm gonna right click here, go to add new item
现在我只是当着你们的面做这个
now I'm just gonna do this live in front of you guys
实际上我之前还没准备好, 所以希望一切顺利
I haven't actually prepared this earlier, so hopefully it goes well
然后, 不管如何, 就是class VertexArray
then, anyway, so class VertexArray
就像我说的, 我希望能有一些缓冲
as I said, I want to be able to have some kind of buffer thing
所以我可能想要的是
so potentially what I might want is
我们需要一个构造方法和一个析构方法
well, we'll have the constructor and a destructor
那基本上会触发OpenGL, 实际去做我们需要做的
and that's going to basically just hit OpenGL, and actually do what we needed to do
当我们真正创建一个布局的时候, 我的意思是当你思考它的时候
when we actually create a layout, I mean when you think about it
这个vertexAttribPointer应用于当前绑定的缓冲区
this this vertexAttribPointer applies to the currently bound buffer
所以我们真正需要做的是, 我想我们确实需要
so all we really need to do is, I guess we do need to
比如一旦我们创建了顶点缓冲区, 然后就添加它
like once we actually create the vertex buffer, and we add it
我们确实需要将它绑定到特定的布局, 不是吗
we do need to bind it to a certain layout, don't we
所以也许也许根本不值得
so maybe maybe it's not even worth having
顶点数组实际上存储顶点缓冲区, 或对顶点缓冲区的引用
the vertex array actually store vertex buffers, or references to vertex buffers
它可能会对我们有用, 让我们把某个布局绑定到顶点缓冲区
it might just be useful for us to actually bind a certain layout with a vertex buffer
那是当前绑定的
that's currently bound
如果这说得通的话, 那么, 我真的要这么做
if that makes any sense, so I'm actually gonna do that
因为这对我们做起来更简单, 更快
because it's gonna be a little bit easier and faster for us to do
而不是包含缓冲区之类的东西
so instead of us containing buffers or anything
我们将要做的是包含一个潜在的布局
what we are going to do is contain potentially a layout
事实上, 我可能会做的是我想做的一件随机的事情
in fact, what I might do this is a bit of a random thing that I was thinking of doing
我们实际上可以做的是改变它
what we actually might do is change this around
因此, 这个做的是在OpenGL状态上设置所有东西
so that, what this literally does is just set everything up on OpenGL state
并没有在CPU上存储任何状态
and not really store any state on the CPU at all
那么, 因为我们真正需要做的是
so, because really what we need to do
比如这样做的好处是, 我们不需要每次都设置布局
like the benefit of this is,  that we don't need to keep setting the layout every single time
因为顶点数组
because the vertex array
这儿太热了, 顶点数组实际上为我们存储了状态
so hot in here, the vertex array actually stores that state for us
所以我们需要做的基本上就是
so what we just need to do is basically say
嘿, 这是缓冲, 这是布局, 让它一起工作
hey, here's the buffer, here's a layout, make it work together
那么让我们至少从那个开始, 看看我们得到了什么
so let's let's at least start with that, and we'll see where we get
那么我将写入void AddBuffer
so I'm going to say void, I don't know, AddBuffer
我不擅长给东西命名, 这很难, 老兄很难
I'm not great at naming things, it's hard, man it's hard
所以我们这里要做的就是接收一个VertexBuffer类型的参数vb
so what we'll do is we'll take in a VertexBuffer here vb
然后我们也需要一个布局
and then we'll also have a layout
那么就是VertexBufferLayout类型的参数layout
so buffer vertex buffer layout also layout
好了, 那么, 需要创建两个东西
all right, so two things that need to get created
那么首先, 我们已经有了VertexBuffer, 显然我可以在这里包含它
so first of all, we already have VertexBuffer, obviously I can just include that here
当然, 我已经创建了这个, 注意, 要在源文件夹中
and of course, I've gone ahead and created this, note in the source folder
所以让我们把那个移到源文件夹中
so let's move that into the source folder here
好了, 很好, 我们有了顶点缓冲区, 那么然后
okay, good, so we have vertex buffer, and then
这并不包括在内, 是的, 我猜这只是智能跟踪
which is not being included, yes, it is just IntelliTrace, I guess
然后是VerticeBufferLayout, 我马上会在这儿创建它
and then VerticeBufferLayout is something, I'll make here as well
那么就是VertexBufferLayout
so we'll say, VertexBufferLayout
并且这就是我们的布局类
and this is kind of going to be our layout class
这可能会有一些
which will probably have some kind of
我可能就创建这个吧
I might just make this
我实际上可能移动这个东西,
I'll probably move this thing actually, we'll need that though
那么就叫它VertexBufferElement吧, 或者LayoutElement之类的,  我不知道
so we'll say vertex buffer element or layout element, or something like that, I didn't know
命名太难了, 伙计
again names a hard man
所以这实际上就是用这些元素填充一个向量
so what this is going to really do is just have a vector filled with these elements
VertexBufferElement, 就叫m_Elements
VertexBufferElement, m_Elements
包含vector, 好了
will include vector, okay
然后我们能用这个VertexBufferLayout()做的是
and then what we can do with this VertexBufferLayout is really just
我会写一些东西, 它会是一个模板
I'll write something and it'll be a template
我们可以把一些值放进去, 或者我们可以输入一个类型
that we can actually just push some kind of value in, or rather we can push a type in
这就是为什么它是一个模板
really that's why it's a template
你马上就会看到这个的原理了
you'll see how this works in a minute
在这个例子中, 我们只用static_assert(false)
for this case, we're just going to static_assert false
因为我们不处理这个, 这是如果类型还没匹配
because we don't actually handle this, this is if basically the type is unmatched
因为我们接下来要做的是创建一堆模板专用
because what we're about to do next is actually create a bunch of template specializations
这将是一个Push, 我们只需要浮点数, 我们可以把一些浮点数放进去
so this will be a Push, for let's just a float, where we can push a number of floats in
然后这个要做的就是m_Elements.push_back()
and then what this is really going to do is m_Elements push_back
我们要做的是, 让我们想想我们这里需要什么
and what we'll do is, so let's think about what we actually need in this
我们看一看这个VertexAttribPointer, 需要一个索引
if we look at VertexAttribPointer, we need an index
需要一个count, 那么我们已经有了, 我猜就是这儿指定的这个
we need a count, so we've kind of got count, I guess count is what we specify here
这里我们肯定需要一个count, 我就创建一个unsigned int count
so we definitely need a count here, I'll just make an unsigned int count
我们需要一个能够处理的类型, 和是否标准化以及一个步幅
we need a type which we can handle, we need normalized, and we need a stride
并且我想我们也有了一个偏移量
and I guess we also have an offset
所以我们真正需要的是在VertexBuffetElement中
so really all we need here is inside VertexBuffetElement
我们只需要无符号整型count
we just need unsigned int count
和一个也是无符号整型的type, 因为它是个OpenGL类型
we need the type which is also an unsigned int, because it's a OpenGL type
最后我们还需要一个属性, 那就是它是否被标准化了
and then finally we need one more thing, and that is whether or not it's normalized
所以就是布尔normalized
so we'll say bool normalized
那么count和normalized, 就让它们保持那样吧
so count and normalized, we'll leave in like that
我可能不会, 我的意思是对于浮点型之类的数据
I might not, I mean for floats and stuff like that
真的不太需要normalized, 我们可以先不考虑normalized
we don't really need normalized, we might just leave normalized out for a bit
那么push_back会推回其中一个
so push_back is going to push back one of these
所以我们需要这个count
so we're going to have the count which is just count
我们会有一个type, 我要把它移到第一个
we're going to have the type, which I'm actually going to move to be the first thing
所以我们有type, count和normalized
so we have type count and normalized
所以type在这里就是GL_FLOAT
so the type is going to be in this case GL_FLOAT
因为这是个浮点型专业化
because where this is the float specialization
那么就是GL_FLOAT, count就是count
so GL_FLOAT, count going to be count
至于normalized, 我们暂时就用硬编码false吧
and normalized, for now we're just going to hardcode to false
现在我们需要包含OpenGL来做这个
now we are going to have to include OpenGL to actually do this
如果你处理的是多个接口
you could just if you were dealing with multiple apis
而你不想包含OpenGL
and you didn't want to include OpenGL
那么我认为这对我来说就是glew, 对吧
then I think this is just to me of glew, right
然后你基本上就会有一些
then you could just basically have some
你可以复制所有这些定义的实际定义
you could just copy across the actual definitions of all of those defines right
那么GL_FLOAT就有一个数字值
so GL_FLOAT has a numeric value
你可能会, 我的意思是, 如果我来到这儿
you could be like, I mean, if I go into this
你知道的, 你可以复制一堆这些, 然后把它们放到你的源代码中
you know, you could just copy a bunch of these, and literally put them into your source code
这样你就不会包含整个OpenGL头文件
and so that you're not actually including the entire from OpenGL header
因为你可能没有访问权限, 并且仍然希望编译此代码
because you might not have access to that, and you still want this code to compile
而可能有一些不支持OpenGL的平台, 这就是你可以做的一个例子
and platforms that might not support OpenGL, that's an example of what you could do
因为我不想绑定这个OpenGL特定
because I'm not trying to tie this  OpenGL specific
但在这里, 很明显它就是
but in this case, obviously it is
所以就是那样
so that's that
在这儿添加一些空格
I'm just gonna make some space here
所以我们有了浮点型的Push, 让我们至少再试一个
so we have float, let's try like one more at least
再说一次, 我是想到就这样做了
again, I'm just gonna add these as they come in I think
那么搞一个unsigned int, 可能GL_UNSIGNED_INT作为type,  然后count和false, 没毛病, 这个非常基本
so unsigned int, might be GL_UNSIGNED_INT as the type, count and false, right, this pretty basic
在这个例子中, 我可能还会做的一件事是
one thing I might also do is, in the case, of like
让我们看看, 可能也需要无符号字符, 基本上就像字节
let's just see, we have unsigned char as well, so like bytes basically
那些我们可能保持不变
those may we may want to keep those
那么我基本上要做的就是改这个normalized
normalized basically so I might do that
并且这个应该是UNSIGNED_BYTE
and this would be UNSIGNED_BYTE
好了, 这只是一个例子, 我们如何实现这个自动化的例子
okay, so just an example of, how we can basically automate this
现在我知道这可能有点让人困惑
now I know this might seem a bit confusing
因为我只是在写代码, 可能并没有解释太多
because I'm just writing code, and not really explaining much of it probably
但是所有的这些都要联系在一起
but all this is going to tie in together
当我们在VertexArray类中
when we actually are in the VertexArray class
实际上一切都是由我们自己来设置的
actually setting everything up through ourselves
所以那就是布局
so that's the layout
如果我们来到这儿, 首先我们需要一些东西
if we go down here, we need a few things first of all
我们实际上需要一种获取步幅的方式, 所以一定要有GetStride
we need a way to actually get the stride, right, so GetStride definitely needs to be a thing
我可能会跟踪它, 所以我就返回m_Stride
and I'll probably keep track of that, so I'll just say return m_Stride
我们也需要获取这些实际的元素, 那么就是vector
we also need a way to get these actual elements, so vector VertexBufferElement
抱歉, GetElements() const
sorry, GetElements const
返回m_Elements, 有点长这行, 希望你们能看见
return m_Elements, pretty long line, hopefully you can see it
所以stride方面
so stride wise
我们可以维护一个stride, 那么就是unsigned int m_Stride
we might just maintain a stride, so unsigned int m_Stride
我实际上会在头文件中实现这整个东西
I'm actually just gonna implement this whole thing I think in the header file
所以我们会把步幅初始化为0, 然后每次我们这样做的时候
so we'll set the stride to zero to begin with, and then every time we do this
基本上就是m_Stride加上
we basically want to say m_Stride plus equals
我们推入的实际数据的字节大小
the size of the actual thing that we're pushing back
所以, 在这里, 它就是四个字节
so in this case, it's going to be four bytes
你可能需要做的就是编写某种函数来转换gl类型
what you probably want to do is write some kind of function that converts a gl
你知道的, 比如类型id这些, 那么就是把一个GL类型转成实际字节大小
you know, like type id thing, so a gl type one into an actual size
这样你基本上就像这样sizeof(GL_FLOAT), 那应该还是不错的
so that you can basically just be like sizeof GL_FLOAT, and that'll be fine
但我们暂时采用硬编码写这个
but we're just going to hard write this for now
所以我猜你也可以写sizeof(float), 或者是像那样的sizeof(GLfloat)
so you could also write sizeof float I suppose, or sizeof GLfloat like that
那可能是合理的
that probably be reasonable
我想我们暂时就保持那样吧, 这里是GLuint
we'll keep it as that for now I think, GLuint
以及这里会是GLbyte
and this will be the GLbyte
好了, 酷, 所以这儿还是挺简单的
okay, cool, so this is pretty simple here
我希望你们能理解这儿做了些什么
I hope you kind of understand what's going on here
我们基本上只是维护了一大堆实际的元素, 那构成了我们顶点缓冲区
we're just maintaining basically a bunch of actual elements, that make up our vertex buffer
或者说是我们维持了就像
or rather we're maintaining like
你知道的这儿两个浮点型, 三个浮点型的
you know, if we have two floats here three floats there
但我们得到了一个我们缓冲区的实际布局
but we've got an actual layout for our buffer
我们能做的就像
and what we can do, like
每个元素的索引很明显就是它在我们实际数组中出现的索引
the index of each element is obviously the index has it appears in our actual vector
然后等到了绑定这些的时候
and then when it comes time to bind all this
或者更确切地说, 是时候把顶点缓存和顶点布局结合起来了
or rather when it comes time to bring a vertex buffer with a vertex layout
我们实际上可以在顶点数组中设置那个, 那么就让我们在这里做一下吧
we can actually set that up in vertex array, so let's do that here
所以我会包含VertexBufferLayout
so I'll include VertexBufferLayout
实际上, 我需要为我们的顶点数组创建一个cpp文件
and I'll actually have to create a cpp file for our vertex array
所以让我们快速创建那个吧
so let's just quickly create that
好吧, 就是那样, 完成了, 好了, 那么包含Vert吧
well, that's right, done, okay, so include VertexArray
当我回到这儿
if I go back here
就右键, 为一切方法创建具体实现
I'm just going to right click, and create method implementations for everything
所以一开始, 我们不会从任何事情开始
so the beginning, we won't start with anything really
然后在AddBuffer这里, 那个要做的就是绑定缓冲区
and then AddBuffer really, all that's going to do is bind the buffer
然后它将基本上设置所有这些东西
and then it's going to basically set all this stuff up
那么我们缓冲区的布局就是这两行代码
so we have these two lines of code which is our buffer layout
复制那个, 然后粘贴到这儿
I'm going to copy that, I'm going to paste that in here
接下来我们会包含, 我想可能是Renderer
we're going to include, I guess the Renderer
这个包含了OpenGL和CLCall宏指令
which will should include OpenGL and the GLCall macro
然后我要做的基本上就是在这儿使用const auto
and then what I'm going to do is basically just use constant auto here
因为我不想写出完整的类型
because I don't want to type out the whole type
就会得到我们的elements等于layout.GetElements()
we'll get our elements equals layout.GetElements
然后就是循环elements中的每一个const auto element
and then for each constant auto element in elements
实际上对它们都是进行这种处理
we're going to actually do all this stuff
所以我要把这变成一个一般的全循环
so I'm actually gonna change this to be a normal full loop
所以就是 for (unsigned int i)
so for i equals, it'll be an unsigned int
i = 0; i < elements.size(); i++
unsigned int equals zero, is less than elements size, i++
const auto& element = elements[i]
const auto element equals elements i
我只是在迭代我们在实际布局类中的元素向量
so I'm just iterating through that vector of elements that we have over here in our actual layout class
这里就是这个东西
this is this thing here
然后把i作为启用我们实际的VertexAttribArray()的参数
and we're going to enable i as our actual VertexAttribArray
最后这里也是i
and finally this is going to be i
这里是element.count, 这里是element.type
this is going to be element.count, this is going to be element.type
这里是element.normalized, 那么如果它是标准化的, 对吧
this is going to be element.normalized, so if it is normalized, right
因为这个实际上是个布尔
because this is actually a bool
让我现在这里换下行
and let me just drop this down online
看吧, 你们就会看到
see, you guys can see
如果它是标准化的, 如果这是true
if it's normalized, if that's setted true
我的意思是, 说实话, 我回到这里
I mean, to be honest, I might just go back here
实际上把它作为一个整型或其他的存储
and actually store it as an int or something
那么我们就是看到
so we'll see
我改成了 unsigned char normalized, 我们不需要作为整型保存
I'm unsigned emmm char normalized, we didn't need to store as an int
虽然, 在内存对齐下, 它可能是一个整型
although, with a lime memory alignment, it probably will be an int
不论如何, 但不会影响到无符号字符normalized
anyway, but doesn't matter unsigned char normalized
那么基本上我们这里就是GL_FALSE, 这里是GL_TRUE
so basically we'll just have this to be GL_FALSE, GL_TRUE
这里也是GL_FALSE
and this will be GL_FALSE as well
这样我们所要做的就是在顶点数组中
and that way all we have to do is in vertex array
不用任何转换, 直接写上element.normalized
we don't do any kind of transformation, we can just do add on element.normalized
现在这个就是stride, 那么这个就是layout.GetStride()
now this is the stride, so this will be layout.GetStride()
然后这里就是offset, 所以我们实际上要在这儿计算这个offset
and then this will be the offset, so the offset we can actually calculate here
那么就是unsigned int offset = 0, 把那个offset放在这儿
so unsigned int offset equals zero, we pump that in here offset
然后我们就是简单地增加offset
and then we simply increment the offset
所以就是 offset += element.count
so offset plus equals element.type, sorry element.count
我们确实需要知道元素的大小
and we do need to know the element size which
我不这么认为, 我实际上把它保存在这儿, 还是挺好的
I don't think, I'm actually storing here, which is great
那么, 我们也需要把这个转换成常量空指针类型, 顺便说一下
so, we also need to const cast this to a const void pointer, by the way
那个是错的, 好了
that's that error, okay
那么我们需要知道每个类型的字节大小
so we need to know the size of each type
所以我可能会做的就是做我说要做的事情
so what I might do is actually do that thing, that I was talking about doing
在一个VertexBufferLayout里面
which is inside a VertexBufferLayout
实际上, 我可能会在VertexBufferElement中
I might actually even inside VertexBufferElement
创建一个static unsigned int GetSizeOfType()或其他方法
I'll make a static unsigned int get size get size of type or something
然后这基本上就是无符号整型type, switch(type)
and then this will basically be unsigned int type, switch on type
那么这个分支, 你知道的, GL_FLOAT, 就返回4
and then case you know GL_FLOAT, return four
然后是GL_UNSIGNED_INT, 返回4
unsigned int, four
我们唯一支持的另一个就是UNSIGNED_CHAR, 返回1
and the only other one we support which is unsigned char, return one
抱歉, 应该是BYTE
sorry I'll just byte
就是刚刚那里写的, 那很好, 好了, 酷
which I might have just, yeah that's good, okay, cool
那么现在让我把这个东西对齐吧
so now this becomes let me just align this stuff
返回0, 我们应该在这里断言false
return zero, and we should assert false here
我想那个断言应该在我们的Renderer中
and I guess that assertion stuff is inside our Renderer
那么让我包含这个Renderer吧, 好了, 酷, 那么我们继续
whoops so let me just include the Renderer, okay cool, so there we go
我喜欢那样缩进这些
I like to indent these a bit like that
但我们继续, 那么就是441, 显然, 这是为了确保你做对了
but there we go, so four four and one, obviously this is make sure you get this right
确保你支持当前支持的所有类型, 你当前支持我们刚做的那三个类型
and make sure you support all the types, that you currently support we're just doing three
当我们增加一些更多的类型时, 我们会扩展这个
when we add some more types, we will expand all of this
GetSizeOfType, 我现在可以用这个
GetSizeOfType, I can now use with this
那么为了代替这个
so instead of this
那就是这个VertexBufferElement::GetSizeOfType()
being that it'll just be buffer, sorry VertexBufferElement GetSizeOfType
然后这个type就是GL_FLOAT
and then the type is GL_FLOAT
然后这个也是一样的, 除了GL_UNSIGNED_INT
and then this will be the same, but for UNSIGNED_INT
这个也是一样的, 除了GL_UNSIGNED_BYTE, 好了, 看起来不错
and then this will be the same but for UNSIGNED_BYTE, okay, looks pretty good to me
现在, 明显的是, 在我们的VertexArray中
and now obviously inside our VertexArray
实际上, 我们可以看到, offset += element.count *
we can actually see, offset plus equals element.count
* VertexBufferElement::GetSizeOfType(element.type)
times VertexBufferElement GetSizeOfType element.type
好了, 所以这就是我们的AddBuffer方法, 你可以看到, 它做了很多事情
okay, so that is our AddBuffer function, you can see, it does quite a lot of things
但是它做的主要的事情还是, 绑定这个实际的顶点缓冲区
but the main thing it does is, bind the actual vertex buffer
然后设置那个布局
and then set up all that layout
现在, 明显的是, 我们实际上不得不创建这个顶点数组
now, we have to actually create the vertex array, obviously
那么, 让我们就去做那个吧
so let's do that
回到头文件(VertexArray)
I'm going to go back to the header file
添加一个无符号整型成员m_RendererID, 就像那样
added an unsigned int m_RendererID, just like that
我想我们就在这儿设置它吧, 那么让我们在这儿向下滑一点
we're going to set it up here, I guess, so let's just go down here
从Application.cpp中复制我们需要的, 基本上就是这个代码
and copy what we have from Application, which is basically this code
那么就把这个改成m_RendererID, 然后我们绑定它
so we're going to m_RendererID here, and then we'll we'll bind it well
不过在这里, 我们没必要做绑定
we don't have to bind it in this case
在析构方法中, 我会调用glDeleteVertexArrays(1, &m_RendererID)
in the destructor, I will delete VertexArrays, one and then m_RendererID, like that
好了, 那看起来不错
okay, that looks pretty good
然后在这儿, 我们应该绑定它, 那么我就会调用Bind()
and then over here, we do we should bind it, so I'll just call Bind
不过现在我们这儿还没有Bind方法, 所以就让我们添加那个吧
now we don't have a Bind function here, so let's add that
那么我们有个缓冲区, Bind() const 和 Unbind() const
so we'll have a buffer, and Bind const and Unbind const
我再次使用assistx创建这些实现
I'll make those using visual assistx again
然后(在Bind中)基本上就是调用glBindVertexArray(m_RendererID)
and then we'll basically call glBindVertexArray m_RendererID
对于Unbind, 我们只是绑定0就可以了
and then for Unbind, we'll just bind zero
好了, 所以我们绑定了顶点数组, 那就是我们要处理的, 绑定了缓冲区
okay, so we have where we bind the vertex array, we bind the buffer that we want to deal with
然后为它设置了布局, 那看起来挺不错的
and then we set up a layout for it, and that looks pretty good to me
那么让我们来测试一下这个吧, 回到Application.cpp, 包含VertexArray
so let's test this out, back in Application, I'm going to include VertexArray
然后下来到这里
and then I'm going to go back down here
我们已经创建了VertexArray和VertexBuffer
we make a VertexArray, we make a VertexBuffer
接着创建一个VertexBufferLayout
we're going to make a VertexBufferLayout
现在在我们这个例子这儿, 我们所有的只有这个, 对吧
now all we have in our example here is just this, right
那么从这个实际的GLCall中, 我们知道, 基本上就设置了这两个浮点数
so we know that from this actual GLCall, we basically just set up two floats
所以在这儿, 我所做的就是把这个全部删除
so all I have to do here is I can get rid of all this
然后要做的就是像那样的layout.Push(2)
and just do layout.Push(two), like that
就是那样, 然后就是像那样的va.AddBuffer(vb, layout)
that should be it, and then va.AddBuffer, vb and layout, just like that
好吧, 希望这是有意义的, 这很简单
okay, so hopefully that makes sense, it is pretty straightforward
当我们下来到这儿, 为了替换BindVertexArray, 我们应该使用va.Bind()
and if we go down here, instead of BindVertexArray, we should just be able to do va.Bind() and
一切都应该是正常的
everything should be good
那么就让我们来运行一下这个吧, 希望一切正常
so let's hit f5, and hopefully this works
因为我完全是即兴创作的, 好吧, 我们这里有一个错误
because I just totally improvise all of that, okay, so we are getting an error here
这看起来几乎就是个警告, 真的
this looks like almost a warning really
但我们基本上应该做的就是使用unsigned int count, 而不是int count
but we basically should be having unsigned int count, and not int count
所以我这里就是把这个类型改成像那样的无符号就可以了
so I'm just going to change this type to be unsigned like that
对于所有这些, 不论如何, 很明显, 我们的count不可能是负数
for all of these, obviously we can't have a negative count, anyway
好了, 那应该没问题, 运行一下, 好了
all right, that was good, f5, okay
得到了一个三角形, 那么我们没得到一个实际的正方形
and we get a triangle, so we don't get an actual square
我可能写错了什么东西
so maybe I've done something wrong
让我们回到这儿, 看看发生了什么
let's go back to here, and see what's up
那么我们有四个顶点, 所以它没什么问题
so we had, okay, our vertex buffer has four vertices, so it's pretty good
我们肯定绘制了六个, 那也没啥问题
we're definitely drawing six still and that's all good
让我们调试一下这个吧, 我猜, 看看这个实际的layout
let's actually debug this, I guess, so let's go into our actual layout here
在AddBuffer中, 我需要在这儿设置一个断点
and inside AddBuffer, I'm just gonna place a break point here
关掉这个内存视图
let's close this memory view
在这里多留点空间, f11进入这个函数, 然后
make some more space here, f11 to step in, and then okay
那么我们一定绑定那个VertexArray, 它确实有个实际的RendererID
so we definitely bind that VertexArray does have a it does have a real RendererID
VertexBuffer也绑定了那个, 关于元素, 我们有一个元素
VertexBuffer bind will bind that, elements, we have one element
这也是我们字节大小的类型, 这个count是2, normalized是0
it is the type as well of our sizes, the count is two, normalized is zero
到这里, 看起来都没啥问题
looks pretty good to me so far
来到这儿, 当然, 我们启用了这个索引0
step into here, we enable this index zero, of course
element.count是2, type是那个, normalized是那个
element.count is two, type is that, normalized is that
layout.GetStride()就是stride, 就是4, 哈, 这就是问题所在了
layout.GetStride() was to stride four, four seems, ah so there's the problem
这个步幅是4
the stride is four
但显然应该4 * count, 而这里是2
but it obviously should be four times the count, which in this case is two
所以我们要做的就是返回VertexBufferLayout, 确保那个stride就是
so what we need to do is go back to VertexBufferLayout, and make sure that the stride is
实际上应该sizeof(type)*count
actually the sizeof type times the count
所以我忘记了乘以count
so I forgot to multiply by the count
致命错误啊, 伙计, 把那个count移到第一个来
fatal, man, might move the move it and make the count first
那么就是count * stride, 好了, 继续, 接收的是2, 运行一下
so count times the stride, allright there we go so take 2, f5
然后继续, 我们得到了像平时一样的实际的正方形, 好了, 所以就是这样
and there we go, we get our actual square as usual, allright, so that's it
这就是整个实现
that's gonna wrap up this implementation
我们很快就在顶点数组上组合起来了
that we've quickly thrown together over vertex array
如何实际地抽象它以及布局部分
how to actually abstract that as well as a layout part
这里最重要的是, 我想表达的是这个实际的布局想法, 对吧
the big thing here, I guess capture is this actual layout idea, right
我们实际上提供了我们自己的高层次布局
we're actually providing our own layout in a very kind of high-level sense
我们基本上就是这样表达了
we're basically saying that
嘿, 我这儿有两个浮点数, 处理一下它吧
hey, I have two floats here, deal with it, OpenGL
那真的真的很有用
and that's really really useful
因为如果你在使用
because if you were if you were to use
像批量渲染接口和一个引擎等等
like multiple rendering apis and an engine or whatever
你显然想有一个通用的表达方式
you obviously would want to have a generic way of saying
这个就是我的缓冲区的布局, 那正是我们刚才在这儿做的
this is the layout of my buffer, and that's exactly what we've done over here
很明显, 在这段代码中, 如果我们有几样东西, 也许我们有, 你知道的
obviously with this code, if we had several kind of things, maybe we had, you know
一种3D位置, 然后是3D法线
a 3D kind of position, then a 3D normal
然后像是2D纹理坐标
and then like a 2D texture coordinate
我们可以这样做, 当我们实际添加数学、数学类型和其他东西时
we could just do this, when we actually add maths and mathematical types and stuff
我们甚至可能有一些类似于math::vec2的东西
we might even have something like math vec2
就能够这样表示, 这儿有一个vec2
and just being able to say, we have one vec2 here
可能是一个vec3的实际位置或任何东西
maybe one vec3 for the actual position or whatever
那也会非常有用
that will be useful as well
我们真的可以在将来把它扩展到相当好的程度
and we can really expand this to be pretty good in the future
好了, 因此你们有任何问题, 请在下面的评论区留言
alright, so any questions that you guys have, leave them in the comments below
我觉得这一期和其他的有点不同
this episode I think was a little bit different than all the other ones
我的意思是, 我在你们面前直播撸码
I mean I kind of just programmed live in front of you guys
这感觉起来几乎就是个直播间
this almost felt a little bit of like a livestream
一边解释着我实际在做什么
and may actually explaining what I'm doing along the way
让我知道你对这种形式的看法
let me know what you think of this kind of format
随着我们开始接触更为严格的OpenGL东西
as we start to get into more serious OpenGL things
我不确定我能不能慢慢来, 我是说
I'm not sure if I can take this slow, I mean like
现在我已经录了29分50秒了
I've been recording for 29min 50 seconds at this point
就像, 这会是很长的一期
like, it's this is gonna be a huge episode
我基本上是以最快的速度完成了这件事
and I basically got through this stuff as quickly as I could
是的, 一定要让我知道你对这个的看法
so yeah, definitely let me know what you think about this
如果你能跟得上这一切, 希望你能
if you were able to follow along and all of that, hopefully hopefully you were
我就不需要做更多的解释了
and I don't need to kind of explain too much more
希望大部分是有意义的, 除此之外
hopefully most of this made sense, but other than that
如果你喜欢这个视频的话, 请留下你的赞吧
leave a like if you enjoyed this video
如果你想帮助支持这个系列
if you wanna help support this series
你可以通过patreon.com/TheCherno来支持我
you can go to patreon.com/TheCherno
像往常一样对我所有的赞助人大声呼喊, 是你们让这一切成为可能
huge shout out as always to all of my wonderful patrons that make this stuff possible
一定要帮助支持这个系列啊
definitely helps support the series there
如果你喜欢我做的这些还想看到更多的话
if you like what I'm doing here and want to see more
因为没有你们, 就没有这个系列
because this stuff really wouldn't be here without all those wonderful people
下一期, 我们会说着色器
next time, we're gonna talk about shaders
以及我们如何抽象那个
and how we can actually abstract that
基本上, 我认为, 看看这个, 这就是我们剩下的一切
that's basically I think, looking at this, that's like all we have left
我认为, 然后, 当然是渲染器啦
I think, oh and then, of course the renderer
所以我们肯定会用我们方法抽象这个东西
so we're definitely on our way to kind of abstructing a lot of this stuff
事实上, 当我在这里的时候, 我注意到我们仍然有这个顶点数组代码
actually while I'm here, I noticed that we still have this vertex array code
那么让我们删除所有顶点数组代码
so let's just remove all that vertex array code
所以我们有了这样一个漂亮的代码
so we have this nice and to set up like that beautiful
然后是BindVertexArray(0)这些
and then BindVertexArray(0) and all of that
我们不需要那个了
we don't really need that there
所以我们就让它保持这样吧
so we'll just kind of leave it as is
实际上, 当我们测试解绑一切时
and in fact since we are kind of testing Unbinding everything
我可能基本上会调用va.Unbind()代替刚刚那个
I might just call va.Unbind instead of which just does that basically
这期我确实写了不少代码
now I did write quite a bit of code this episode
如果你想要这些源码
if you would like access to the source code
你可以通过访问patreon.com/TheCherno帮助这个系列
that you could go to patreon.com/TheCherno helps the point series
你就会得到所有这些东西的源码, 一期接一期的
and you will get access to episode by episode kind of source code for all this stuff
可能会比较有用
could be useful
因为当然, 我确实写了不少的代码, 如果你遇到了一些出错的
because of course, I did write quite a bit of code, and if you got something wrong
它确实是个不错的比较方法
it's a really good way to kind of compare
并且确保一切都是正常的
and make sure that everything is working for you
不论如何, 希望你们喜欢这期视频
anyway, hope you guys enjoyed this episode
下一期, 我们说说着色器, 在那之后可能就是渲染器
next time, shaders, then after that probably renderer
在那之后, 我们真的就要添加数学库之类的东西了
and then after that, we really have to add maths and stuff like that
然后我们就会接触到一些更令人兴奋的东西
and then we'll move on to some more exciting things
像纹理, 以及像把显卡和这些东西实际联系起来
like textures, and like actually getting graphics and stuff together
我们应该能够去探索发现
we should be able to find
喔, 这个系列是, 它有相当多要做的
oh, this series is, it's quite a bit of work
让我告诉你OpenGL吧, 不管如何, 下次见, 拜
let me tell you OpenGL, anyway, see you guys next time, bye